A Finding Aid to the Henry and Rose Pearlman Papers, 1893-1995, bulk 1950-1980, in the Archives of American Art AAA.pearhenr
Archives of American Art
Henry and Rose Pearlman papers
bulk 1950-1980
1893-1995
AAA.pearhenr
Archives of American Art
4.3 Linear feet
The records of the Henry and Rose Pearlman papers measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1893 to 1995 (bulk 1950-1980). The collection documents the activities of Post-Impressionist and Modern art collectors Henry and Rose Pearlman through correspondence, research materials, exhibition catalogs, photographs, and clippings.
Pearlman, Henry
Biographical Note
Henry Pearlman (1895-1974), a lifelong resident of New York City, rose through the ranks of the business world to found his own company, Eastern Cold Storage, in 1919. In 1925, Henry married Rose. In the early 1940s, Pearlman purchased a few realist paintings, but it wasn't until his 1943 purchase of Chaim Soutine's Village Square that he was inspired to build what would become a noted collection of Post-Impressionist works. Over the next three decades, Pearlman acquired numerous works by such well-known artists as Soutine, Modigliani, Cezanne, Van Gogh, Renoir, Manet, Matisse, and Toulouse-Lautrec, in addition to those of lesser-known artists. In the early 1950s, Pearlman began collecting Cezanne watercolors. These paintings would become the cornerstone of his collection and would be exhibited around the world. Pearlman died in 1974, leaving his wife, Rose, to manage his collection until her death in 1994. From the mid-1970s, the Pearlman Collection has been on long-term loan to the Art Museum of Princeton.
The Pearlmans founded the Henry and Rose Pearlman Foundation in the 1950s. Much of the Pearlmans' artwork is now officially owned by the Foundation.
Scope and Content Note
The Henry and Rose Pearlman papers measure 4.3 linear feet and document the activities of art collectors Henry and Rose Pearlman through correspondence, research materials, exhibition catalogs, photographs of artwork and exhibitions, and clippings ranging from 1909 to 1995 (bulk 1950-1980). Most of the materials relate to artists and pieces represented in the Pearlmans' collection, although a small amount of material concerns works considered or researched by Pearlman, but not purchased.
The bulk of the collection concerns the lending, reproduction, and exhibition of works of art owned by the Pearlmans and their foundation. Supplemental research material such as exhibition catalogs, photographs of artworks, and articles and clippings on artists, artworks or other private collections, make up most of the remainder. Oversized materials include a catalogue of the Pearlman Collection, a portfolio of reproductions of the Cezanne watercolors belonging to the Pearlmans, and photographs comparing Toulouse-Lautrec's Parody of the Bois Sacre aux Arts et Muses to the original.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into four series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: General Collection Files, 1950-1995 (Box 1, 5; 8 folders)
Series 2: Artists' Files, 1909-1995 (Boxes 1-5, MGP 5; 3.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Museum Files, 1951-1994 (Box 4; 20 folders)
Series 4: Personal Files, 1966-1993 (Box 4; 5 folders)
Provenance
The Henry and Rose Pearlman papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2004 by Dorothy Edelman and Marge Scheuer, daughters of Henry and Rose Pearlman, care of the Henry and Rose Pearlman Foundation.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Henry and Rose Pearlman in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2011, and total 5446 images.
Blank pages, blank versos of photographs, photographs of artwork, duplicates, and medical, legal, and personal financial documents have not been scanned. In most cases, only the cover, title page, and individual relevant pages have been scanned from published materials. A few documents were not scanned at the request of the Princeton Art Museum because they contained sensitive information.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Cézanne, Paul, 1839-1906; Degas, Edgar, 1834-1917; Gogh, Vincent van, 1853-1890; Kokoschka, Oskar, 1886-; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-; Modigliani, Amedeo, 1884-1920; Pearlman, Rose, b. 1901; Soutine, Chaim, 1893-1943; The Henry and Rose Pearlman Foundation; Art--Collectors and collecting--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- General Collection Files, 1950-1995; Series 1; (Box 1, 5; 8 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains general materials relating to the Pearlmans' collection as a whole. It contains informational sheets and photocopies of a card catalog index describing various pieces in the collection; legal documents reflecting the donation of artwork from the Pearlmans' private collection to that of their foundation; a short, illustrated volume written by Mr. Pearlman describing his experiences building his collection; exhibition catalogs for collection-wide shows; newspaper clippings about those exhibitions; and photographs of the collection as installed in Mr. Pearlman's New York office. Artwork information includes an appraisal of the collection from 1989.
  Arrangement note
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Personal financial information has not been scanned and only the cover, title page, and individual relevant pages have been scanned from published materials.
  - Artwork Information, circa 1950-1974, 1989; (Partially scanned) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Collection Card Catalog, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Henry and Rose Pearlman Foundation, Legal Documents, 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1952-1976; (Oversized item housed in Box 5, F1) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book by Henry Pearlman, Reminiscences of a Collector, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Henry Pearlman's Office, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Exhibition Catalog, 1974 (Box 5 (sol), Folder 1)
- Artists' Files, 1893-1995; Series 2; (Boxes 1-5, MGP 5; 3.2 linear feet)
  This series contains materials relating to many of the various artists represented in the Pearlmans' collection. These materials generally include correspondence with museums, galleries, and other experts regarding the purchase, exhibition, reproduction or authenticity of a piece; artwork loan forms; research documentation; magazine articles and newspaper clippings relating to the artists or exhibits of their works; exhibition catalogs; and photographs, negatives, and slides of artwork. To maintain original order, enclosed loan forms, newsletters, and photographs have been filed with their correspondence.
  Some of the artists significantly represented in this series include Cezanne, Modigliani, Degas, Soutine, and Van Gogh. The Kokoschka files include personal correspondence from the artist and his wife to the Pearlmans; the Kokoschka and Lipchitz files contain photographs of the artists with some of their work. The Various section encompasses materials relating to no particular artist or to an artist not represented fully enough for a subseries.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Photographic reproductions of artwork have not been scanned and only the cover, title page, and individual relevant pages have been scanned from published materials. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Cezanne, Correspondence, 1948-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cezanne, Correspondence, 1962-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cezanne, Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cezanne, Exhibition Catalogs, 1950-1974; (Oversized item housed in Box 5, F2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cezanne, Booklet, Color Test of Mt. St. Victoire, circa 1950-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cezanne, Booklet, Understanding Cezanne, circa 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cezanne, Articles and Clippings, 1920-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cezanne, Articles and Clippings, 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cezanne, Articles and Clippings, circa 1920-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cezanne, Photographic Material, Artwork, Black and White Copy Prints, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cezanne, Photographic Material, Artwork, Negatives and Transparencies, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cezanne, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Courbet, Correspondence, Printed and Photographic Material, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Daumier, Correspondence, Printed and Photographic Material, 1958-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Degas, Correspondence, 1958-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Degas, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Degas, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Degas, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1927-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Degas, Articles and Clippings, 1921-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Degas, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gauguin, Correspondence, 1949-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gauguin, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1893-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gauguin, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gauguin, Articles and Clippings, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gauguin, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1930-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hartley, Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kokoschka, Correspondence, General, 1948-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kokoschka, Correspondence, with Artist, 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kokoschka, Appraisal, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kokoschka, Exhibition Catalog, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kokoschka, Articles and Clippings, 1948-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Kokoschka, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Kokoschka, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lipchitz, Correspondence, 1957-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lipchitz, Exhibition Catalogs, 1951-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lipchitz, Articles and Clippings, 1954, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lipchitz, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lipchitz, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Manet, Correspondence and Printed Material, 1909-1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Manet, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Marchutz, Printed Material, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Marchutz, Leo Marchutz School of Painting and Drawing, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Margules, Poem, "Passage to Parthenon,", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Matisse, Correspondence, 1952-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Matisse, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Matisse, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Modigliani, Correspondence, 1951-1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Modigliani, Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Modigliani, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1931-1951 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Modigliani, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Modigliani, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Modigliani, Articles and Clippings, 1951-1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Modigliani, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Modigliani, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Molenaer, Correspondence and Printed Material, 1947-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pisarro, Printed and Photographic Material, 1904-1975 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Prendergast, Correspondence and Printed Material, 1960, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Renoir, Correspondence, 1952, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Renoir, Exhibition Catalogs, 1910-1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Renoir, Articles, 1919, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Renoir, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Robert, Correspondence, 1939-1975 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Robert, Printed and Photographic Material, circa 1950-1974 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Soutine, Correspondence, 1952-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Soutine, Research Information, circa 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Soutine, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1928-1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Soutine, Books and Exhibition Catalogs, 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Soutine, Articles and Clippings, 1932-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Soutine, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Correspondence, 1953-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Exhibition Catalogs, 1938, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Le Bois Sacre aux Arts et Muses, circa 1950-1974; (Oversized item housed in Box 5, F3) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Articles and Clippings, 1938-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Toulouse-Lautrec, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Van Gogh, Correspondence, 1949-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Van Gogh, Research Information, 1906-1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Van Gogh, Exhibition Catalogs, 1901-1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Van Gogh, Articles and Clippings, 1892-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Van Gogh, Photographic Material, Artwork, Glass Negatives, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    (4 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 5)
  - Van Gogh, Photographic Material, Artwork, Prints and Negatives, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Van Gogh, Photographic Material, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Various, Correspondence, A-C, circa 1944-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Various, Correspondence, D-M, circa 1944-1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Various, Correspondence, N-R, circa 1944-1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Various, Correspondence, S-Z, circa 1944-1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Various, Correspondence, unidentified, circa 1944-1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Various, Exhibition Catalogs, 1921-1936 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Various, Exhibition Catalogs, 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Various, Exhibition Catalogs, 1944-1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Various, Exhibition Catalogs, 1969-1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Various, Private Collection Tours, Individuals, 1958-1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Various, Private Collection Tours, Institutions, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Various, Private Collection Tours, American Federation of Arts, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Various, Private Collection Tours, Museum of Modern Art, 1955-1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Various, Articles and Clippings on Private Collections, circa 1916-1979 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Various, Articles and Clippings, 1930-1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Various, Articles and Clippings, 1955-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Various, Articles and Clippings, circa 1930-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Various, Photographic Material, Artwork, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Various, Photographic Material, Unidentified Artwork, Prints, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Various, Photographic Material, Unidentified Artwork, Negatives, circa 1950-1974; (Not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Various, Photographic Material, Unidentified Salons, Original Prints, circa 1950-1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, 4 Glass negatives (Box MGP 5)
  - Oversize Cézanne Watercolor Prints, circa 1950s (Box 5 (sol), Folder 2)
  - Oversize Toulouse-Lautrec Parody Comparison, circa 1950-1974 (Box 5 (sol), Folder 3)
- Museum Files, 1951-1994; Series 3; (Box 4; 20 folders)
  This series contains materials relating to the exhibition of the Pearlmans' collection at museums around the United States. These materials typically include correspondence and loan forms, as well as photographs of many exhibitions. Exhibitions have been identified from documents within the collection where possible. These files also contain extensive correspondence between Mrs. Pearlman and the staff of the Art Museum of Princeton, where the Pearlmans' collection remains on long-term loan.
  - Art Museum of Princeton, Correspondence, 1973-1979; (Partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Art Museum of Princeton, Correspondence, 1980-1984; (Partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art Museum of Princeton, Correspondence, 1985-1989; (Partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Art Museum of Princeton, Correspondence, 1990-1994; (Partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, Correspondence, 1952-1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, Printed Material, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, Photographs of Exhibition Installation, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - The Brooklyn Museum, Correspondence, 1955-1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - The Brooklyn Museum, Printed Material, 1964, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, Correspondence and Photographs of Exhibition Installation, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, Photographs of Exhibition Installation, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Knoedler Gallery, Correspondence and Photographs of Exhibition Installation, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Correspondence, 1952-1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Printed Material, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Museum of Modern Art, Correspondence, 1950-1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Correspondence, 1964-1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - National Gallery of Art, Correspondence, 1972-1988 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, Correspondence and Photographs of Exhibition Installation, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Various, Two Japanese Museums, Booklets, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Various, Photographs of Unidentified Exhibition Installations, circa 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Personal Files, 1966-1993; Series 4; (Box 4; 5 folders)
  This series contains a small amount of the Pearlmans' personal and business correspondence including letters, cards, and stock transactions; newspaper clippings relating to the Frigitemp company; an assortment of business cards and handwritten lists and notes; and personal photographs.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Personal medical information has not been scanned.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1966-1992; (Partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Business Correspondence, 1978-1993 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Business-Related Clippings, 1974-1971 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1975 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Photographic Materials, Original Prints and Slide, circa 1930-1991 (Box 4, Folder 32)